Guide to the Robert L. Bracklow Photograph Collection 1882-1918 (Bulk 1896-1905) PR 8
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Alland Purchase
  - Subseries II. Prints
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1634-1642, [1892]-1913 (Box 15, Folder 78)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1643B-1647A, 1914-1917 (Box 15, Folder 79)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1648-1653, 1911-1916 (Box 15, Folder 80)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1653A-1664, 1911-1916 (Box 15, Folder 81)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1665-1676, 1902-[1916] (Box 15, Folder 82)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1677-1690, 1889-1916 (Box 16, Folder 83)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1690A-1699, 1890-1891 (Box 16, Folder 84)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1700-1709, 1909-1910 (Box 16, Folder 85)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1710-1714B, 1900-1913 (Box 16, Folder 86)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1715-1722, 1913, undated (Box 16, Folder 87)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1723-1729C, 1911-1916 (Box 16, Folder 88)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1730-1744, 1897-1913 (Box 16, Folder 89)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1745-1752, 1891-1913 (Box 17, Folder 90)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1753-1761, 1897-1911 (Box 17, Folder 91)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1762-1776, 1916, undated (Box 17, Folder 92)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1779A-1789, undated (Box 17, Folder 93)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1790-1802, 1913, undated (Box 17, Folder 94)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1802A-1816, 1882-1913 (Box 17, Folder 95)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1818-1849B, undated (Box 17, Folder 96)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1849C-1858B, 1897-1902 (Box 18, Folder 97)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 1859-2004, [1890]-[1918] (Box 18, Folder 98)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2008-2025, 1890-[1898] (Box 18, Folder 99)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2026-2039, 1890-1895 (Box 18, Folder 100)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2040-2053, 1892, undated (Box 18, Folder 101)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2055-2069, 1895, undated (Box 18, Folder 102)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2070-2084, 1889-1898 (Box 18, Folder 103)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2085-2097, 1892-1895 (Box 19, Folder 104)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2099-2120, 1892-1895 (Box 19, Folder 105)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2121-2158, undated (Box 19, Folder 106)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2160-2174A, 1912, undated (Box 19, Folder 107)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2175-2190, 1901, undated (Box 19, Folder 108)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2190A-2202, 1890, undated (Box 19, Folder 109)
    - Prints, 8 x 10"--#s 2203-2214, undated (Box 19, Folder 110)
- Series II. Trappan Gift
  The series is arranged into five subseries: Albums, Documentary Material, Logbooks, Prints, and Lantern Slides.
  - Subseries I. Albums
    Albums were titled by Bracklow. John Judson Trappan, Ruth Trappan's father, catalogued the album photos in a logbook, which can be found in subseries III. It is unclear whether Bracklow numbered the albums or if the numbers were added by Trappan. Most albums cover a discrete event or trip to a city, although some encompass several different locations. Some albums contain newspaper articles that relate to the photos within. Bracklow may have intended some of these albums to be gifts or meant for sale; many are inscribed on the inside cover with his name or initials, the date, and sometimes the words "limited edition."
    - Dewey Days [unnumbered], 1899 Sep.-Oct. (Box 20)
    - 1. Glimpses Through the Camera, 1898 May-Oct. (Box 20)
    - 2. Vacation, 1896 Jul.-Aug. (Box 21)
    - 3. Three Outings, 1909 May-Jun. (Box 22)
    - 4. New York, 1902 Sep.-Nov. (Box 22)
    - 5. Dewey Days, 1899 Sep.-Oct. (Box 22)
    - 6. Dewey Arch, 1899 Oct. (Box 23)
    - 7. Manhattan from Within and Without, 1900-1902 (Box 23)
    - 8. Manhattan Old and New, 1899 Feb.-1903 Jan. (Box 23)
    - 9. Riverside Drive, Madison Square, 1901 Oct.-1902 Apr. (Box 24)
    - 10. Gotham, 1902 Apr.-May (Box 24)
    - 11. New Rochelle, Hunt's Point, New York, Ravenswood, 1900 Sep. (Box 24)
    - 12. Lorelei Fountain - Heine Monument, 1899 Jul.-1902 (Box 25)
    - 13. Fort Washington, N.Y. and a bit of Fort Lee, N.J., 1903 Jan.-1908 Nov. (Box 25)
    - 14. Weehawken, N.J. to Yorkville, N.Y, 1900 Jul.-Aug. (Box 25)
    - 15. New Brunswick, N.J., Manhattan, N.Y., Brooklyn, and bits picked up on an attempt at an International Yacht Race, 1901 Sep.-Oct. (Box 26)
    - 16. An October Day on Long Island, 1896 (Box 26)
    - 17. Flushing, Bensonhurst, Medford, Charlestown, Roxbury, Marblehead, Mass., 1900 Jun. (Box 26)
    - 18. Marblehead, 1901 Oct. (Box 27)
    - 19. Lexington & Marblehead, Mass., 1907 Aug. (Box 27)
    - 20. Monterey, Berkshire County, Mass., 1903 (Box 27)
    - 21. September Days in Berkshires, 1903 Sep. (Box 28)
    - 22. May Days in Berkshires, 1905 May (Box 28)
    - 23. Harper's Ferry, 1900 (Box 28)
    - 24. Harper's Ferry, 1900 (Box 29)
    - 25. [Untitled], 1891-1914 (Box 29)
    - 26. [Untitled], undated (Box 29)
    - 27. [Untitled], undated (Box 30)
    - 28. War Bulletins, 1898 Jun. (Box 30)
  - Subseries II. Documentary Material
    This subseries incorporates ephemera belonging to Bracklow and material related to Bracklow accumulated by Ruth Trappan. Bracklow material includes unused boards for a planned Marblehead album, Bracklow's notes of titles in negative boxes (these are loose, as compared to those laid in to the 1903 datebook in Subseries III), a map of Long Island, a postcard of Marblehead, MA, and several envelopes with Bracklow's stamp on them. Other material consists of a folder of 7 pictures and cabinet cards of Mary Granger (two are taken by Bracklow), Ruth Trappan's copy of Mary Black's Old New York in Early Photographs 1853-1901 (New York: Dover, 1973), and typed captions describing Bracklow photos from a planned exhibit by Ruth Trappan.
    - Bracklow's negative box notes, undated (Box 31, Folder 111)
    - Envelopes, postcards, etc., undated (Box 31, Folder 112)
    - Photos of Mary Granger, 1897, undated (Box 31, Folder 113)
    - Trappan's photo captions, undated (Box 31, Folder 114)
    - Trappan's copy of Old New York in Early Photographs, 1973 (Box 31, Folder 115)
  - Subseries III. Logbooks
    This subseries includes two logbooks, one kept by Bracklow and one created by John Judson Trappan, Ruth Trappan's father. The Bracklow logbook is a commercially published datebook for 1903 (perhaps of a kind sold by Bracklow in his stationery store) in which he has recorded the titles of negatives in a number of negative boxes. Bracklow ignored the datebook's printed dates and instead wrote about eight titles per page. This book also contains several loose pieces of paper, which seem to have once accompanied negative boxes, on which photograph titles are also recorded. The other logbook is a composition book in which John Trappan recorded the subjects of the photographs in Bracklow's albums. A photograph of Bracklow is pasted to the front. It is unclear why Trappan undertook this project, but the book, which is in good condition, provides a quick reference to the albums.
    - 1903 Datebook, 1903, undated (Box 31, Folder 116)
    - Logbook of prints in albums, undated (Box 31, Folder 117)
  - Subseries IV. Vintage Prints
    Some of these prints have Bracklow's notation along the bottom. Most are undated. Trappan grouped the photos by city or state, and this arrangement has been kept as much as possible. Trappan also wrote on the back of some of these prints, and in this case signed her notations "R.T." Many of these scenes are from the same trips documented in the photo albums, such as Fort Lee and Somerset, N.J., and New Rochelle, N.Y. Others are from towns either not well represented, or otherwise unrepresented, in the albums and Alland's prints, such as Bridgehampton, N.Y., Sag Harbor, N.Y., and Boston, MA. Three of these prints are cyanotypes. Several landscapes, of an unidentified location, show intense light contrast. The two still lifes in this subseries (in box 33, under the heading "Other") appear to be the only studio shots in the collection. Prints are organized by size, by state and city, when known, and then by subject.
    - 7 x 9" prints (7), 1901, undated (Box 31, Folder 118)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Connecticut--Clinton, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Connecticut--New London, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Connecticut--New Milford, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Connecticut--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Maine, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Boston, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Great Barrington, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Lenox, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Lexington, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Marblehead, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Medford (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Newburyport, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Stockbridge, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Massachusetts--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Hampshire (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Jersey--Hackensack, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Jersey--Jersey City, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Jersey--Morristown, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Jersey--Somerville, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New Jersey--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--Bridgehampton, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--East Hampton, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--Hudson River, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--New Rochelle, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--New York City, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--Sag Harbor, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--New York--Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Pennsylvania, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Rhode Island, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Virginia, undated (Box 32)
    - 5 x 7" prints--Unidentified location--Bridges, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Buildings, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Churches, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Houses, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Landscapes, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Other, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Rivers, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Streets, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Waterfronts, undated (Box 33)
    - 5 x 7" prints---Unidentified location--Views, undated (Box 33)
  - Subseries V. Lantern Slides
    The 7 slides in this subseries include several portraits of Bracklow, including one shot of him and a friend in a cow yoke. A modern copy print was made of this image for the 1983 exhibit, and can be found in the collection file. Other slides show Bracklow's friend Moses Joy, Grace Church, and Fulton market.
    - 8 Lantern Slides, undated (Box 33)
- Series III. Other Sources
  This series is made up of the small amount of Bracklow material acquired from other sources.
  - 1949 Gift
    Mrs. Hopper Striker Mott donated one "Glimpses Through the Camera" mounted photo.
    - 1949 Gift, undated (Box 34, Folder 119)
  - 1983 Gift
    Alfred Lowenherz gave the N-YHS a photograph of a Camera Club party ca. 1900. Bracklow is pictured at the far right. Lowenherz made the print from an original photograph either for, or because of, the 1983 Bracklow exhibit.
    - 1983 Gift, [1900] (Box 34, Folder 120)
  - 1984 Purchase
    N-YHS purchased 8 "Glimpses Through the Camera" mounted photographs. These images show New York scenes: Washington Bridge, Rose Street, Brighton Beach Hotel, two children in front of the first City Hall site in New York, the Herald Building, the Pedestal for the Columbus Statue in Columbus Circle, Park Row with newspaper buildings, and Murray Street. Bracklow's interest in the changing cityscape can be scene in his captions for these photos. He notes that the Herald Building is "now torn down," and the buildings shown on Murray Street are about to be torn down.
    - 1984 Purchase, 1888 Apr.-1892 Oct. (Box 34, Folder 121)
  - 1992 Gift
    Dealer Charles Schwartz donated 14 of the "Glimpses Through the Camera" mounted photographs. At the time of the donation N-YHS chose images which were not otherwise represented in the Collection. Most of these views lack either Bracklow's stamp on the back, captions for the photographs, or both. Two identified photographs depict Fourth Avenue Presbyterian Church and Bloomingdale Reformed Church. Unidentified images show men with cattle, the First Methodist Church on John Street, churches, country houses or hotels, a pier, and rocks along the ocean.
    - 1992 Gift, 1890-91, undated (Box 34, Folder 122)
  - 2002 Gift
    Charles Schwartz gave two more "Glimpses Through the Camera" photographs in 2002. One of these shows St. Paul's Chapel at Broadway and Fulton Streets. The other image is of the corner of Broadway and Murray Street in March 1892.
    - 2002 Gift, 1892, undated (Box 34, Folder 123)